Guide to the Sam Wallach Papers TAM.241
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Sam Wallach Papers
Bulk, 1935-1999
1921-2001
TAM.241
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
3.75 linear feet in 3 record cartons and 2 manuscript boxes
The Sam Wallach Papers include materials from Sam Wallach (1909-2001) and Rose Russell (1899-1965) New York teachers who were active in the Teachers' Union in the 1940s and 1950s. Wallach was fired by the New York City Board of Education in 1951 for refusal to cooperate with various bodies investigating Communism.
Wallach, Sam
Scope and Content Note
The Sam Wallach Papers include materials from Sam Wallach (1909-2001) and Rose Russell (1899-1965). The collection includes Wallach’s correspondence; clippings; materials relating to Wallach’s suspension, dismissal and subsequent reinstatement; his FBI surveillance file and items from his second career working with the mentally retarded. The bulk of Rose Russell’s material is correspondence relating to the Teachers’ Union and photographs of union events. The collection also includes audio materials (vinyl records and reel to reel tapes).
Custodial History note
Gift of Joan Wallach Scott, 2001. The Rose Russell material was entrusted to the Wallach family by Harris Russell, Rose Russell's husband, after her death in 1965.
The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2001.201, 2001.202, and NPA.2008.006.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically. The collection is composed of the following four series:
Series I: Personal Papers
Series II: Rose Russell Material
Series III: Subject Files
Series IV: Photographs
Series V: Audiovisual Materials
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frederic Ewen Audiotape and Videotape Collection. Contains the transcript of an interview with Sam Wallach on May 2, 1990 (OH 52)
Historical/Biographical Note
Born in Dolina, Poland, on July 1, 1909, Sam Wallach came to the United States with his parents when he was about 10 months old. He grew up in Brooklyn, the oldest of four children. After attending Brooklyn Technical High School, he studied at City College of the City of New York, graduating in 1929. He was a playground director in Brooklyn and then a high school teacher of economics and history. He joined the Teachers' Union and became one if its leaders, serving as President from 1945 until 1948.
In 1948, Wallach was called by the Hartley Congressional Labor Committee in its investigation of the Teachers Union. He repeatedly asserted that the Committee had no right to investigate personal or political beliefs. His statement, published in The New York Times, was defended by sixty notable thinkers and educators, including Albert Einstein.
In 1949 The New York State Legislature passed the Feinberg Law, which demanded that the Board of Education seek out subversives and Communists and bar them from teaching. From 1951 to 1956, dozens of city school teachers were dismissed and blacklisted; Sam Wallach was one of the first.
He worked in a variety of jobs after his dismissal, including creating educational filmstrips for National Teaching Aids, and then took a position at Maimonides Developmental Center advocating for mentally retarded children. He helped formulate strategy for "mainstreaming" students and for establishing residential group homes for the retarded.
In December, 1976, as he was about to retire from Maimonides, he and nine of the other teachers who had been dismissed in the 1950s, were reinstated and awarded pension benefits by the New York City Board of Education.
Sam Wallach was married for 56 years to Lottie Tanenbaum. They had two daughters, Joan Wallach Scott and Ruth Wallach Frankel. Wallach died on February 14, 2001, at the age of 91.
O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964; Russell, Rose.; Teachers' Union of the City of New York.; Wallach, Sam; Academic freedom |z New York (State) |z New York.; Black-and-white photographs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Eulogies.; Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance files.; Legal documents.; Minutes.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs); Teachers' unions |z New York (State) |z New York |x History |y 20th century.; Teachers' unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1937-2001
  Scope and Content Note
  Directly related to Sam Wallach's personal life, this series contains correspondence, notes, published and unpublished writings, and transcripts of several interviews. Legal documents, newspaper clippings and official communications relating to his suspension and dismissal from public school teaching, along with letters of support from former students, are included in the series. There are also many items concerned with his subsequent reinstatement. Of particular interest is his lengthy FBI file, obtained under the Freedom of Information/Privacy Act in 1998.
  - "Abolish the Regents Examinations in New York City," Sam Wallach, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Education of the City of New York, 1951-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1967-1987, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Harris Russell and the Wallachs, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eulogies and Written Tributes (A-H), 1962-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Eulogies and Written Tributes (J-V), 1945-1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Feinberg Law: Opinions Concerning Constitutionality (U.S. Supreme Court), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Feinberg Law: Opinion Declaring Law Unconstitutional (Supreme Court of the State of New York), 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Freedom of Information/Privacy Act: Request, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Freedom of Information/Privacy Act: Response - FBI File, Samuel Wallach (I), 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Freedom of Information/Privacy Act: Response - FBI File, Samuel Wallach (II), 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Freedom of Information/Privacy Act: Response - FBI File, Samuel Wallach (III), 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Freedom of Information/Privacy Act: Response - FBI File, Samuel Wallach (IV), 1952-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interviews, 1986, 1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Maimonides Develpmental Center, 1974-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Maimonides Developmental Center: Correspondence, 1974-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Maimonides Developmental Center: Retirement, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorial Invitation, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "More than Good Will Is Needed," Samuel Wallach and Herbert M. Chamais, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Reinstatement (I), 1972-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Reinstatement (II), 1972-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Reinstatement: Clippings, 1948-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Reinstatement: Resolutions and Agreement, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Suspension and Dismissal, 1948-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Suspension and Dismissal: Official Communication, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Suspension and Dismissal: Legal Documents, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Teachers' Union, 1938-1950, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Teaching, 1937-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series II: Rose Russell Material, 1921-1965
  The bulk of this series is correspondence, much of it in the form of tributes to Rose Russell on celebrating the tenth and twentieth anniversaries of her association with the Teachers' Union. Tenth anniversary tributes (1954) come from union representatives, university professors, attorneys, politicians and religious leaders; correspondents include such well-known individuals as W. E. B. DuBois, Joseph P. Selly, Morris Schappes, Cedric Belfrage and Scott Nearing. In 1964, at the twentieth anniversary celebration, Russell was presented with several leather binders full of tributes. Among them are letters and telegrams from notables such as Martin Luther King, Jr. and his wife, Coretta Scott King, Langston Hughes, Abraham Beame, Frederic Ewen, I. F. Stone, Irving Adler, Linus Pauling, Alexander Meiklejohn, Corliss Lamont, and a host of state senators and assemblymen, journalists, Board of Education members and staff, union members, court officers, representatives of a wide variety of organizations and personal friends. The Irish playwright Sean O'Casey corresponded with Ms. Russell for a number of years. One of his letters in the collection, a moving condolence written on November 20, 1963, after the assassination of President Kennedy, was subsequently published in The New York Times.
  - Bachelor of Arts Diploma, University of Michigan: Rose Russell (Gutterman), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Lamont, Corliss, 1954, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Meiklejohn, Alexander, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: O'Casey, Sean, 1956-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Pauling, Linus, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: Various, 1953, 1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Memorial and Obituary, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Scroll of Honor Award (Teachers' Union), 1947 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Scroll of Honor Award (Teachers' Union): Presentation Frame, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Tenth Anniversary Testimonial Dinner: Correspondence, 1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Twentieth Anniversary Tribute to Rose Russell, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Twentieth Anniversary Tribute to Rose Russell: Album of Tributes (Volume 1), 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Twentieth Anniversary Tribute to Rose Russell: Album of Tributes (Volume 2), 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Twentieth Anniversary Tribute to Rose Russell: Presentation Album, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1935-1999
  This series contains a variety of materials touching on subjects and individuals of interest to Sam Wallach with particular emphasis on the Teachers' Union and its activities. There are also many items collected by Wallach on the topic of mental retardation.
  - Adler, Irving and Joyce, 1993, 1999, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anti-Communism, 1941-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cammer, Harold I., 1983-1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Clippings and Articles: Various Topics, 1945-1996, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Education: General, 1952-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jews for Racial and Economic Justice, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jews for Racial and Economic Justice: Marshall T. Meyer Risk-Taking Award, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Katz, Blanche and Al, 1989-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mental Retardation (I), 1969-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mental Retardation (II), 1969-1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mental Retardation: Employment, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Mental Retardation: Employment, 1977-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mental Retardation: Minutes - Brooklyn Boro-Wide Council for the Mentally Retarded, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Non-Sectarian Anti-Nazi League to Champion Human Rights: Brochure, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Social Frontier: Articles, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Teachers' Union, 1937-1964, 1996, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Teachers' Union: Award - Abraham Lederman, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Teachers' Union: Award Plaque ("To Eleanor Roosevelt..."), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Teachers' Union: Conferences, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Teachers' Union: Draft Article Annotated by Sam Wallach, [1997] (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Teachers' Union: Film - Dreamers and Fighters, 1949-1997 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Teachers' Union: Teacher News Issues, 1938-1959 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Teachers' Union: Teacher News Issues, 1960-1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Teachers' Union: Teaching Materials, 1940, 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - United Federation of Teachers, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Zeal for American Democracy": Special Issue of School Life, Feb 1948 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Series IV: Photographs, circa 1940-1970
  Approximately 225 black and white mostly 8 x 10 photographs and 13 black and white slides separated from the Sam Wallach Papers. Most of the images document the activities of Rose Russell in the Teachers Union, and its successor organization, the United Federation of Teachers. Many of them were shot by the photographer and Teacher’s Union member, Mildred Grossman. Dates appear range from 1940s to the 1960s.
  - 7x11 Prints and Smaller, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Slides, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series V: Audiovisual Materials, circa 1949-1958
  This series includes 23 records and 10 reel-to-reel tapes. Many of the records are labeled recordings of Teachers Union events, most seeming to involve Rose Russell. There is also an interview of Rose Russell by Mike Wallace
  - Reel-to-Reel Tapes
    - Unlabeled (4 reels), undated (Box 4)
    - 7th Annual Educational Conference Recordings (3 reels), Mar 28, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Wilson-Hutchins Hearings (1 reel), undated (Box 4)
    - Hodges and Lumpkin (1 reel), 1958 (Box 4)
    - Rose & Prof Dunham (1 reel), undated (Box 4)
  - Vinyl Records (Box 6)
    - Rose Russell Interview by Mike Wallace on "Nightbeat", May 15, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Excerpts and Highlights - Teachers Union Annual Conference, undated (Box 5)
    - 5 Unlabeled Records, undated (Box 5)
    - Complete Speeches of Rose Russell, John De Boer and Abe Lederman from Teachers Union Annual Conference, 1949 (Box 4)